LORENZO SILECI

Grantham Research Institute \diamond London School of Economics and Political Science Houghton Street, London WC2A 2AE

RESEARCH INTERESTS

I am an environmental and development economist. My current research focusses on the environmental justice implications of climate policy and on the interplay between poverty alleviation and environmental conservation and restoration. I approach these questions by leveraging big data, remotely sensed information and current quasi-experimental methods in causal inference and machine learning.

CURRENT EMPLOYMENT

Grantham Research Institute for Climate Change and the Environment, LSE

Postdoctoral Research Officer

The Economics of Biodiversity Additionality (BIOADD)

EDUCATION

London School of Economics and Political Science, UK

September 2018 - April 2023

PhD in Environmental Economics

Thesis: "Causal Inference in Spatial Environmental Economics"

Examined by Prof. Paul Ferraro and Prof. Hendrik Wolff

Awarded without corrections

London School of Economics and Political Science, UK

September 2016 - 2017

MSc in Environmental Economics and Climate Change (Distinction)

University of Sydney, Australia

January 2015 - July 2015

Postgraduate Coursework Exchange Program (Distinction)

University of Florence, Italy

September 2011 - December 2014

BA in Economics and Trade (110/110 cum laude)

PUBLICATIONS

- 3. Groom, B., Palmer, C., and Sileci, L. (2022). "Carbon emissions reductions from Indonesia's Moratorium on forest concessions are cost-effective yet contribute little to Paris commitments". Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 119 (5), February 2022. [Available at PNAS]
- 2. Bates, A. E. et al. (2021), "Global COVID-19 lockdown highlights humans as both threats and custodians of the environment". Biological Conservation 263, 109-175. [Available at Biological Conservation]
- 1. Amador-Jiménez, M., Millner, N., Palmer, C., Pennington, R.T. and Sileci, L. (2020). "The Unintended Impact of Colombia's Covid-19 Lockdown on Forest Fires". Environmental and Resource Economics 76, 1081-1105. [Available at Environmental and Resource Economics]

WORKING PAPERS

Palmer, C., Groom, B., Sileci, L., and Langton, S. (2023) "Biodiversity-food trade-offs when agricultural land is spared from production". Geography and Environment Discussion Paper Series (34). Department of Geography and Environment, LSE, London, UK. [Revise and resubmit at Americal Journal of Agricultural Economics] [Available at LSE]

WORK IN PROGRESS

Sileci, L. "Carbon Pricing in Presence of Permeable Borders: The Case of British Columbia's 2008 Carbon Tax" (presented at LSE Geography)

Sileci, L. "Carbon Pricing with Regressive Co-benefits: Air Quality and Health Effects from British Columbias Carbon Tax are Positive but Unequally Distributed" (presented at LSE, AERE, BIOECON)

Pagel, J. and Sileci, L. "More Than Just Carbon: The Socioeconomic Impact of Large-Scale Tree Planting" (presented at CEC-PSL)

Perra, E., Sanfilippo, M. and Sileci, L. "Oil Spills, Agricultural Production and Deforestation in Nigeria"

Sileci, L., Palmer, C., and Groom, B. "Policy Layering and Biodiversity Additionality in Indonesia"

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

GY476: Applied Geographical Information Systems

MT 2022

London School of Economics and Political Science

· MSc-level core module in Geographic Data Science

GY222: Applied Environmental Economics

LT 2023

London School of Economics and Political Science

· BSc-level core module in Environmental Policy with Economics

GY499: Dissertation MT-LT 2023

London School of Economics and Political Science

· Methodological supervision to postgraduate students' dissertations

GY350: Dissertation MT-LT 2019

London School of Economics and Political Science

· Methodological supervision to undergraduate students' dissertations

CONFERENCES AND INVITED PRESENTATIONS

2023: IAERE, envecon, AERE, EAERE, BIOECON, CEC-PSL, GRI Empirical Seminar

2022: LSE Geography, GRI, LSE WIP Seminar

2021: LSE Geography, GRI, UniFi DELoS Seminar

2020: SWEEET, LSE Geography, GRI

2019: LSE Geography, GRI, LEEP

2018: LSE Geography, LSE South East Asia Centre, BIOECON

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

European University Institute

January 2021 - August 2021

Research Associate, Robert Schuman Centre for Advanced Studies, Global Governance Programme

- · Data visualisation and preliminary analyses;
- · Write-up of the Report's data section and technical appendix;
- · Development and deployment of the website containing the online appendix for the EUI's GGP "Services and Economic Development in Africa" project.

European University Institute

May 2020 - January 2021

Research Assistant, Robert Schuman Centre for Advanced Studies, Global Governance Programme

· Data collection, cleaning, and harmonisation for the EUI's GGP "Services and Economic Development in Africa" project.

Carbon Cap Management LLP, London, UK

May - June 2019

External Consultant

· Technical report on the U.S. Regional Greenhouse Gas Initiative (RGGI), EU ETS and Western Climate Initiative (WCI) cap-and-trade carbon markets.

LSE Middle East Centre

January - April 2018

Research Assistant

· Project on the Implications of Counter-Insurgency Policies in Palestine: "Do counter-insurgency policies change the way people make decisions? Evidence from a Natural Experiment". Elicitation of Risk and Time Preferences on a dataset of Palestinian households situated in proximity to the West Bank wall.

Grantham Research Institute for Climate Change and the Environment

2017-2018

Research Assistant

· Literature Review for a paper on UK FDI and green innovation. Data Cleaning and Analysis on the ONS UK ARDx Dataset. Accredited Researcher at the UK Office of National Statistics.

LSE, Department of Geography and Environment

2017-2018

Research Assistant

· GIS Analyses and data cleaning for a paper on Land Sparing in Agricultural Landscapes (presented at ENVECON2018, London, UK).

TECHNICAL SKILLS AND LANGUAGES

Statistical Software R (advanced), STATA (proficient), Python (beginner)

Other Software & Tools LATEX, Google Earth Engine, QGIS, RMarkdown, GitHub, MS Office

Languages Italian (native), English (fluent), Spanish (basic)

AWARDS AND SCHOLARSHIPS

Productivity and Merit Scholarship, University of Florence. 2011-2014

Abroad Master Scholarship, Regione Toscana, Italy. €14,000 2016-2017

Research Grant, LSE South East Asia Centre. £5,000.

PhD Research Scholarship, Economic and Social Research Council, UK. Full scholarship. 2018-2022

REFERENCES

Prof. Ben Groom

Department of Economics
University of Exeter

☑ B.D.Groom@exeter.ac.uk

Prof. Paul Ferraro

Carey Business School
Bloomberg School of Public Health
Whiting School of Engineering
Johns Hopkins University

☑ pferraro@jhu.edu

Prof. Charles Palmer

Prof. Hendrik Wolff